Guide to the Stirewalt Family Papers, 1830s-1993
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stirewalt Family papers 1830s-1993
Stirewalt family
6.0 linear feet Extent: 2750 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01256
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The collection was received in several separate gifts between 1988 and 1998.
Biographical Note: Jacob Stirewalt
1805 Born August 17, in Rowan Cty., Va.
1833 Married Henrietta Henkel, New Market, Va.
1837 Licensed by the Tennessee Synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church.
1838 Ordained by the Tennessee Synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church.
1869 Died August 21; buried at Emmanuel Church, New Market, Va.
After his ordination, Jacob Stirewalt served pastorates in Shenandoah, Page, and Rockingham Counties in Virginia. He was an active member of the Tennessee Synod, often speaking at conventions held in Virginia, North Carolina, and Tennessee. He fathered four sons, two of whom became Lutheran ministers, and six daughters.
Biographical Note: Jerome Paul Stirewalt
1850 Born, April 11, New Market, Va.
1873 Ordained by the Tennessee Synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church.
1878 Married to Tirzah A. Coffman, Shenandoah Cty., Va
1914 D.D. Lenoir Rhyne College. Hickory, N.C.
1920 Retired to New Market, Va.
1934 Died; buried at New Market, Va.
Jerome Paul Stirewalt, one of Jacob Stirewalt's four sons, studied theology under pastors of the Tennessee Synod. During his career as a pastor, which spanned from 1874 to 1920, he served fourteen different churches in pastorates in Virginia. Jerome Paul Stirewalt was very active in the leadership of the Tennessee Synod, serving as secretary for six terms, and four terms each as treasurer and president. He was a frequent contributor to Lutheran and secular periodicals and contributed an article on the history of the Tennessee Synod for "The Lutherans in America," edited by E.J. Wolf.
Biographical Note: Martin Luther Stirewalt
1882 Born, July 24, New Market, Va.
1902 A.B. Lenoir Rhyne College, Hickory, N.C.
1906 B.D. Chicago Seminary.
1906-1909 Instructor, Weidner Institute, Mulberry, Indiana.
1907 Married Caroline Dentzer, Chicago, Ill. Ordained, Chicago Synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church.
1909 Professor of Ancient Languages at lenoir Rhyne College.
1921 D.D. Lenoir Rhyne College.
1922-1920 Professor of Practical Theology, Chicago Seminary.
1928 Graduate Study at Northwestern University, Evanston, Ill.
1930-1938 Pastor of a Lutheran Church in Salsbury, N.C.
1951 Retired to Hickory, N.C.
1955-1959 Associate Professor, Lenoir Rhyne College.
1935-1960 Member of the Board of Lenoir Rhyne College.
1960 Died, March 10, Hickory, N.C.; Buried in New Market, Va.
Martin Luther Stirewalt, the only son of Jerome Paul Stirewalt, served as an instructor at the Weidner Institue, a Lutheran School in a suburb of Chicago, from 1906-1909. He was active in the leadership of the North Carolina Synod, serving as vice-president from 1917-1922 and from 1919-1922 was the secretary of the joint commission overseeing the merger of the Tennessee Synod with the North Carolina Synod. He also served on the board of Lenoir Rhyne College from 1921-1922 and again from 1935-1960.
Biographical Note: Catherine A. Stirewalt
1929 B.A., Carthage College.
1938 M.A., New York University.
1939-1941 Traveled to China to study Chinese and to begin missionary work for the Lutheran Church near Tsingtao in the Shantung Province.
1941-1943 Interned by the Japanese in the Weihsien Concentration Camp near Tsingtao, China during World War II.
1943 Repatriated to United States.
1947 Returned to China to resume missionary work for the Lutheran Church. Taught school in a Lutheran Mission near Tsingtao.
1949 Left China as the Communists came to power.
1950 Accepted as a Deaconess in the United Lutheran Church.
Catherine A. Stirewalt is the daughter of Martin Luther Stirewalt. Prior to pursuing her missionary activities, she worked as a high school teacher.
Collection Overview
The Stirewalt Family Papers, 1828-1993 (bulk 1850-1947), are comprised of the personal papers of individuals from four successive generations of the Stirewalt family. The correspondence, writings, diaries, legal/financial documents, photographs, and other miscellaneous papers found in this collection document the Stirewalt Family's personal lives and involvement in the Lutheran Church as ministers, educators and missionaries. The collection is divided into four primary series which reflect the individuals whose papers make up this collection: Jacob Stirewalt, Jerome Paul Stirewalt, Martin Luther Stirewalt, and Catherine A. Stirewalt. The arrangement of the collection is primarily chronological, following the lineage of the Stirewalt family. Subsections within each major series are determined by the type of materials found within the collection and are arranged either chronologically, as in the case of the Diaries and Correspondence Subseries, or alphabetically and thereunder chronologically, as in the case of the Writings Subseries.
The Stirewalt family is descended from Jacob Stirewalt, a minister and member of the Tennessee Synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church. Jacob Stirewalt was primarily active in and around New Market, Va. and Rowan and Shenandoah counties in Virginia. The Subseries related to Jacob Stirewalt includes Correspondence from 1828-1858, Writings (primarily sermons and sermon outlines in German and English) from the 1830s to the 1860s, and Diaries, which includes a Memorandum book where he recorded financial transactions and other records of his career as a minister from 1834 to his death in 1869.
Jerome Paul Stirewalt, the son of Jacob Stirewalt, was also a minister and a leader of the Tennessee Synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church. He served as a minister in several pastorates in Virginia and North Carolina and several terms as president, secretary, and treasurer of the Tennessee Synod in the late 1800s and early 1900s. His papers are primarily composed of Correspondence, 1870-1933, with other ministers, relating to the business of the Tennessee Synod, and with family members. The collection also includes Jerome Paul Stirewalt's Writings, primarily sermons and sermon outlines, and other miscellaneous financial and legal papers. The Diaries Subseries is primarily memorandum books which list the date and location of religious services performed and the topic or title of sermons delivered by J.P. Stirewalt. These books serve to provide a record of Stirewalt's work as a Lutheran minister.
Martin Luther Stirewalt, the son of Jerome Paul Stirewalt, was also a Lutheran minister and educator at Lutheran schools and colleges in Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, and Chicago, Ill. This series includes correspondence, diaries, writings and clippings which provide a picture of Stirewalt's theological education, activities as a minister and educator, and insights into his personal life and familial relationships.
The papers of Catherine A Stirewalt, Martin Luther Stirewalt's daughter, are primarily correspondence written while she was a Lutheran Missionary in China from 1939-1949. This correspondence provides documentation of the Lutheran Church's activities in China prior to and after World War II. Catherine Stirewalt's letters provide a great deal of detail about the daily lives of missionaries in China and some information about the lives of the Chinese people working as instructors or attending the mission school. There is no correspondence from the period of the first two years of World War II when she was interned in the Weihsien concentration camp near Tsingtao, China. Other miscellaneous clippings, photographs, and writings in this series provide further documentation of her experiences in China.
Subject Headings
Stirewalt, Catherine A.; Stirewalt, Jacob, 1805-1869; Stirewalt, Jerome Paul, 1850-1934; Stirewalt, Martin Luther, 1882-1961; Lutheran Church -- Clergy -- Correspondence; Evangelical Lutheran Church -- North Carolina; Evangelical Lutheran Church -- Virginia; Lenoir Rhyne College (Hickory, N.C.) -- Students; Evangelical Lutheran Tennessee Synod; United Evangelical Lutheran Synod of North Carolina; Lutheran Theological Seminary (Chicago, Ill.); Lutheran Theological Southern Seminary (Columbia, S.C.); Clergy -- Southern States -- Correspondence; Lutheran Church -- Clergy; Lutheran Church -- Sermons; Newmarket (Va.) -- Church history; North Carolina -- Church history; South Carolina -- Church history; Missions -- China; Lutheran Church -- Missions; Lutheran Church -- China; Lutheran Church -- Education; Women missionaries -- China -- Correspondence
Contents of Collection
- Jacob Stirewalt Papers
  The papers of Jacob Stirewalt, 1828-1869,are divided into six Subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Diaries, Financial Papers, Legal Papers, and Miscellaneous Papers.
  - Correspondence, 1828-1858, (1 folder) (Box 1)
    Jacob Stirewalt's correspondence is chiefly with members of his family and is arranged chronologically.
  - Writings, 1827-1869, (10 folders)
    The Writings Subseries is primarily composed of sermons and sermon outlines written by Stirewalt in both English and German. This subseries also includes the bound handwritten manuscripts of two short unpublished religious texts authored by Stirewalt and one folder of miscellaneous writings.
    - "Compendium of Theological Treaties,"1827, (1 folder) (Box 1)
      33 pages, bound, handwritten manuscript. Includes several inserted leaves of notes.
    - "Defense of the 6th Article of the Old Constitution of the Evan. Luth. Tennessee Synod,"1869, (1 folder) (Box 1)
      99 pages, bound handwritten manuscript. Subtitled "With Remarks on the Ministerial Office and A Vindication of the Ordination of a Young Minister."
    - Sermons,1830s-1860s and undated, (7 folders) (Box 1)
      Stirewalt's sermons are primarily in English, but several of his early sermons are in German. Many of the sermons exist only as detailed outlines, which may have been used as notes to be referred to when delivering the sermon. The sermons are arranged chronologically, with undated sermons, fragments, and notes grouped at the end of the subseries.
    - Miscellaneous Writings, ca.1850, (1 folder) (Box 1)
      One two-page manuscript in Stirewalt's hand titled "A Brief Admonition to Confession," and a three-page manuscript titled "A Cursory Admonition to Repentance."
  - Diaries, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    The Diaries Subseries includes a Memorandum book providing financial and travel details related to Jacob Stirewalt's ministerial duties between 1834-1869and a small undated notebook containing miscellaneous personal and religious writing and inspirational clippings from the1850s-1860s.
  - Financial Papers,1830s-1860s and undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    The Financial Papers Subseries includes a Memorandum book, dated1860,which provides a partial record of Jacob Stirewalt's expenses from 1860-1864;several documents relating to financial transactions and purchases; and miscellaneous documents, fragments and notes which seem to be related to financial transactions or accountings. This subseries also includes an1864receipt for the purchase of $100 worth of Confederate Bonds.
  - Legal Papers, 1836-1858, (2 folders)
    - "Rev. John N. Stirewalt's Last Will and Testament," 1836, Aug. 16. (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Legal Papers, 1846-1858. (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Papers,1820s-1869, and undated, (6 folders)
    The Miscellaneous Subseries includes assorted personal papers, notes and certificates related to Stirewalt's work as a minister, clippings on various subjects, and writing fragments that are not identified or otherwise classifiable. The subseries is ordered alphabetically by folder title.
    - Marriage License, 1833, Jan.7. (Box 1)
      Jacob Stirewalt's and Hennrietta Henkel's marriage license.
    - Notes and Certificates,1820s-1860s and undated (Box 1)
      Marriage licenses and notes recording the performance of religious services.
    - Notes and Clippings,1850s-1860s and undated (Box 1)
    - Ordination Papers, Jacob Stirewalt, 1837-1839 (Box 1)
    - Picture of Jacob Stirewalt, undated (Box 1)
    - Plans for D. Watkin's wheat fan (Box 1)
      One small series of drawings and notes in Jacob Stirewalt's hand concerning improvements to a wheat fan.
- Jerome Paul Stirewalt Papers
  The Jerome Paul Stirewalt Papers,1859-1933, are divided into 4 subseries: Diaries, Correspondence, Writings, and Miscellaneous Papers.
  - Diaries, (4 folders)
    - Memorandum Book, 1859-1926, (3 folders) (Box 1)
      A note on the title page of this memorandum book states that it was purchased by Jacob Stirewalt in1853.The first third of the volume provides a record of Jacob Stirewalt's ministerial activities, including the time, places, and text of the sermons, funerals, baptisms, confirmations, performed by Stirewalt and his compensation for these duties between1859and his death in1869.The memorandum book was continued by Jerome Paul Stirewalt in1872and provides a similar record of his ministerial activities from that date through1926.The book is in extremely fragile condition and a preservation photocopy is provided for use.
    - Memorandum Book, 1881-1931, (1 folder) (Box 1)
      The first quarter of this memorandum book provides a record of Jerome Paul Stirewalt's ministerial activities at St. Matthew's Church in Mt. Olive, Va. 1881-1883and a detailed record of marriages and funerals performed by J.P Stirewalt between1917and1931.The remainder of the volume provides a record of his expenses and earnings from farming for 1922-1923.
  - Correspondence, 1870-1933, (14 folders)
    The Correspondence Subseries, 1870-1933,is arranged chronologically to the item level. The bulk of Stirewalt's correspondence spans from 1870-1900.There is a gap in the continuity of this subseries after1902,with no letters from1903to1911and very few letters from1911to1933.The letters are primarily correspondence with other ministers concerning administrative activities of the Tennessee Synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church. Many of the letters seem to refer to the solicitation of funds for special projects being undertaken by the Synod and to financial compensations being provided by the Synod to member ministers. The collection also includes some personal correspondence, business correspondence not related to the activities of the Tennessee Synod, and several drafts of letters written by Stirewalt between1911and1912.Also included is a small amount of correspondence received by William J. Stirewalt.
    - General Correspondence, 1870-1892, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1893-1933, (9 folders) (Box 2)
    - Drafts of Letters, 1911-1912, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - William J. Stirewalt, 1898-1904,and undated, (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Writings,1890s-1919, and undated, (8 folders)
    The chronologically arranged Writings Subseries primarily consists of sermons and sermon outlines, the bulk of which appear to be outlines which Stirewalt used as references while delivering the sermons. Most of the sermons are dated and the location where each was written, primarily New Market, Va., is given. The outlines are very detailed, providing titles, and references to biblical texts cited by the sermon or used as evidence to support the theme of the sermon. Three folders of undated sermons are filed at the end of this subseries.
    - Sermons,1880s (Box 2)
    - Sermons, 1890-1899 (Box 2)
    - Sermons, 1900-1905 (Box 2)
    - Sermons, 1906-1909 (Box 2)
    - Sermons, 1910-1919 (Box 2)
    - Sermons, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1857-1941, (11 folders)
    The Miscellaneous Subseries contains primarily materials created or compiled by Jerome Paul Stirewalt. Also included in this subseries are materials created or compiled by members of his immediate family. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by folder title. The Miscellaneous papers consist of legal and financial paper, clippings, notes, documentation referring to the activities of the Tennessee Synod of the Evangelical Lutheran Church, religious pamphlets not authored by Stirewalt, and notebooks that were created by members of Stirewalt's immediate family.
    - Clippings,1884, 1941,and undated, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Clippings and Pamphlets,1894, 1905,and undated, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Deeds and Miscellaneous Legal Papers, 1885-1912, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Estate Papers of Maria C. Stirewalt, 1910-1912, (1 folder) (Box 2)
      Jerome Paul Stirewalt was the executor for the estate of his sister. This part of the collections contains a small amount of correspondence related to the administration of the estate and receipts and financial records generated by the settlement of the estate.
    - Examination Papers, William J. Stirewalt, ca. 1898, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Fire Insurance Documents, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - "Notes on Moral Philosophy," Quintus Stirewalt, 1857-1858, (1 folder) (Box 2)
      A handwritten abstract book created by Quintus Stirewalt while a student at the University of Virginia. Over half of the book is pasted over with clippings of a newspaper column from an unknown source providing details of the Lutheran Church's activities in Indiana, ca.1869.
    - "Presidents Report of the Tennessee Synod,1912", (1 folder) (Box 2)
      24 page pamphlet with a "Presidents Report" written by Stirewalt and providing details of the activities of the Tennessee Synod for1912.
    - "Questions for examining candidates for ordination," undated, (1 folder) (Box 2)
      6 pages "Sermon Sketch" notebook with 38 questions written by J.P. Stirewalt.
    - Receipts and Miscellaneous Financial Records, 1887-1892, undated, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Receipts and Miscellaneous Financial Records.1890s-1920, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - Subscriptions Lists, (1 folder) (Box 2)
      Subscription lists for "History of the Evangelical Lutheran Tennessee Synod" (1890) and "Minutes of the Evangelical Lutheran Tennessee Synod," (1892).
    - "Treasurer's Report of the Tennessee Synod, 1892-1893", (1 folder) (Box 2)
      Draft of a report authored by Stirewalt while serving as treasurer of the Tennessee Synod.
- Martin Luther Stirewalt Papers
  The Martin Luther Stirewalt Papers Series,1899-1959, consists of four subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Diaries, and Miscellaneous Documents.
  - Correspondence 1899-1959, (9 folders) (Box 3)
    The Correspondence Subseries is arranged chronologically and consists of the personal and professional correspondence received by Martin Luther Stirewalt. It includes one folder of letters received from his parents while a student at Lenoir Rhyne College in Hickory, N.C. from 1899-1900;7 folders of personal and professional correspondence received between1905and1952;and one letter book presented to Martin Luther Stirewalt at Christmas in1959which includes letters of condolence he received from professional acquaintances while in the hospital during that year.
  - Writings, 1905-1941,and undated, (18 folders)
    The Writings Subseries is arranged in loosely chronological order and consists of Martin Luther Stirewalt's early religious and professional writings. The subseries is composed of notebooks containing coursework and religious essays written while a student at the Chicago Lutheran Theological Seminary, later student essays, sermons and speeches, and notes and drafts for other religious and professional writings. Many of the sermons included in this subseries appear to have been developed and compiled by Stirewalt as guides to sermon writing and were possibly used as curriculums for courses he taught.
    - Notebook, 1905, May 25. (Box 3)
    - Notebook, 1905, July 24. (Box 3)
    - Notebook, 1905, Aug. 16. (Box 3)
    - Notebook, 1905, Aug. 24. (Box 3)
    - Notebook, 1905, Nov.5. (Box 3)
    - Notebook, 1906, Jan. 11. (Box 3)
    - Essays,1927,and undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      7 handwritten and typescript manuscripts on religious and literary subjects. Possibly written in college and graduate school.
    - Masters Thesis,1928, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      "The Curricula of Selected Lutheran Theological Seminaries in the United States," Northwestern University. 109 pages, typescript with 2 handwritten pages of charts.
    - Sermons, 1917-1932, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      Complete sermons and miscellaneous notes and outlines for sermons.
    - Sermons and Speeches, 1934-1941and undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      8 typescript and handwritten manuscripts of speeches and sermons delivered by Stirewalt. Included is the text of an address delivered in1935titled, "Parish Education Problems and Their Solutions;" a1934sermon titled "Man's Fundamental Need;" and the text of a1941sermon delivered to the religious organizations of Lenoir Rhyne College.
    - Speeches,1941, undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      20 page handwritten draft of speech titled "Progress in Theological Education," read at Stirewalt's induction as Dean of the Lutheran Theological Southern Seminary in1941.17 page handwritten draft of a speech titled "How Men are Called to the Ministry." Also included is a schedule of the induction ceremony.
    - Sermons, undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      179 loose typescript and handwritten sheets that appear to have been held together in a 6" x 9" three ring binder. The typescript and handwritten sermons and outlines of sermons in this notebook may have been used by Stirewalt as a curriculum for a class on sermon writing.
    - Sermons, undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      119 typescript pages in a 6" x 9" black three ring binder, primarily sermons and sermon outlines. Possibly compiled as an educational aid.
    - "Practical Homiletics," undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      75 typescript pages in a 6" x 9" black three ring binder. Appears to be an outline and series of lecture notes for a class called "Practical Homiletics."
    - Notes from biblical and historical texts, undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      Typescript 6" x 9" pages with outlines of New Testament books as well as notes from other historical texts.
    - "First Draft Long Range Policy for the Faculty - Southern Seminary," undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      3 typescript copies of a 4 page policy statement with some annotations.
    - "The Minutes of the United Evangelical Lutheran Ministers and Delegates in the State of North Carolina, 1803-1816," undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      31 page typescript draft of Stirewalt's translation from German of the minutes of early meetings of the Evangelical Lutheran Church in North Carolina.
    - "An Ethical Code for Ministers" undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      5 page typescript of Stirewalt's ethical and behavioral guidelines for Lutheran Ministers.
    - "The Tennessee Synod," undated, (1 folder) (Box 3)
      3 typescript pages of notes made in preparation for writing a chapter for a book on the history of the Tennessee Synod.
  - Diaries, 1904-1952, (3 folders)
    Included in this subseries are two notebooks containing records of sermons delivered and religious services performed by Martin Luther Stirewalt from1904to1952and a desk diary from1942.The sermon records include the title, date and place delivered, and primary biblical references for each of Stirewalt's sermons.
    - Record of Sermons, 1904-1918 (Box 3)
    - Record of Sermons, 1919-1959 (Box 4)
    - Desk Diary,1942 (Box 4)